Ready?!
I'm scaling a glacier right now to show you
a view that most people can never see of a
place we weren't even sure existed until 200years ago.
This... is ... Antarctica! And in 1985,
it became the center of a global crisis. "The
ozone layer still is disappearing." "A mysterious
massive hole." "The ozone is severely depleted."
"Without immediate action, the sun we have always
worshiped, our children will soon fear." Directly
over Antarctica, high up in the stratosphere,
was a massive hole. And if we hadn't done anything
about it, today we'd be living in an alternate
world. By now, a hole would be forming over the
North Pole as well. By 2040, that hole would be
over the entire planet. By 2065, skin cancer rates
would be soaring. If you lived anywhere here, you'd
get a sunburn outside in five minutes. But that's
not the world we're living in. In fact, you've
probably stopped hearing this story altogether.
That wasn't by accident. It was a choice. In fact,
two choices, both of which dramatically changed
the course of human history for the better. So,
let me show you how that happened and what's
about to happen next. Because it turns out
this little sliver at the bottom of the map is
actually the center of our whole planet. And you
need to see this right now because scientists
say that we need to make the next big choice.
I remember hearing all about the ozone hole as a
kid. The situation seemed really dire even at 7
years old, but also really far away. "The problem
is particularly bad in Antarctica." "A hole in the
atmospheric ozone." "Over Antarctica." "Antarctica.""A huge gap over Antarctica." And then one day the
news about it just stopped... and I stopped thinking
about it. Until I got the opportunity to go to that
far away place. We're getting on the plane. Got to
admit I'm a little bit nervous. Turns out getting
to Antarctica is a little sketchy. You can take a
ship from the tip of South America, which is scary
because then you have to cross the Drake Passage,
which is historically known as the deadliest ocean
passage in the world. Three oceans collide here.
There are an estimated 800 shipwrecks somewhere at
the bottom of this passage. Or the other option is
to fly on a plane like this one. We flew from Cape
Town traveling with the White Desert Foundation's
Science Week, which supports scientific research
in Antarctica. The thing about the plane
is it's also not without its scary things
because the runway that we're about to land on
is made of ice. "Please fasten your seat belts."
"Welcome to Antarctica."
Fewer than 5,000 people are allowed on this
entire continent right now. Almost all of
them scientists. No one owns Antarctica. It's an
entire continent run by an international treaty
system for peace and science. But because it's so
hard to get to, doing research here takes a huge
effort. It's typically limited to the Antarctic
summer. Right now, it's summer and the sun never
sets. It's like 10:00 p.m. right now. 10 p.m. to
me because all the time zones meet down here. So,
there's no official time zone at all.
Researchers typically choose the time
zone of whoever gives them food, their supply
base. And to make things even more complicated,
well... it's so slippery and so windy that the
wind is pushing me backwards. Look at this!
The wind is pushing me. The wind I'm
not moving backward. It's just hard to
do anything here. And it wasn't any easier
40 years ago when researchers first noticed
that ozone problem. We are gearing up
for what should be about a 10hour hike.
Now I got to put on these massive spikes to walk
across this ice. I can report it is very cold and
very windy. I didn't quite realize what we were
about to get ourselves into, but what we found at
the end was unlike anything I'd ever seen. Up
here in the stratosphere, all over the Earth,
you'll find a bunch of molecules that shield
us from radiation by absorbing harmful UV rays.
It's like a natural sunscreen for the Earth. This
is the ozone layer. Scientists in this research
station have been watching it for decades. "One
season, they just went, 'That's weird. is really
low. Like what's going on here?'" So, a small team
set out to Antarctica to find out. "Leading the
team is Susan Solomon"... and I called up the
researcher who led that trip. But back then,
she was a 30-year-old scientist with a question.
"A lot of people didn't believe it at first. How
can this be happening? You know, what could
possibly cause this?" What she was about to
discover would forever change the lives of you,
me, and everyone else on this planet. And the
reason that she could figure it out was because
of an incredible decision made decades prior that
changed the course of history. But while I'm here
in Antarctica today, a very real problem is snow
blindness. Because of all the sun reflecting off
the ice. Oh my god. Do not take your sunglasses
off. Snow blindness is a real thing. It's like
looking at the sun. So I had to buy these special
sunglasses. And I'm buying them with this. This
is my real Mercury card. Mercury is the tool that
we've used since we launched HUGE* If True to manage our
finances. I started my Mercury account before I
launched this show. I feel cool. Do I look cool?
Mercury really gets that what I want isn't just
money storage. It's financial tools that help
me actually achieve our big, ambitious, creative
goals. It's why when we got the opportunity
for this trip, we knew we could actually make
it happen. This was by far the biggest trip we've
ever done. This was a ton of planning and a ton
of gear that we needed to buy. But with all of our
finances in one place with Mercury, we could make
a budget and stay within it. They helped us get
the equipment that we needed to stay safe and get
all of the incredible shots that we were dreaming
of. It's all unbelievably intuitive and it's easy
to sign up. Mercury's been great for me and I
think it would be for any entrepreneur or small
company. It's a financial technology company, not
a bank. So, if you want to learn more about what
they can do, check the link in the description or
go to mercury.com. And now I'm ready to go! If you
time traveled back to the 1950s, this incredible
place of peace and science was almost a war zone.
It's the middle of the Cold War. Antarctica is
some of the last unclaimed territory on Earth. So,
of course, countries are trying to grab it. If
you look at a map during that time, it really
looks like pie slices with overlapping claims and
two superpowers saying that they could just claim
it all. "Everybody was like, 'This is crazy.'" But
then one day, a small group of scientists had a
different idea. If you ever find yourself doubting
that a small group of people can change the world...
It's April 5th, 1950. Some of the most famous
geophysicists at the time gather together for a
dinner party. And someone says something like,
'You know, we really should study what's going
on before they like destroy things in Antarctica.'
And they all agree. So they go to the governments
of the biggest countries fighting there and they
say basically, 'Hey, could you just pause on the
claiming land thing like just for 18 months? You
can get right back to it afterward. We promise.'
I'm paraphrasing here a lot. But this proposal
actually works. "And they decided to run a massive
collaborative international program called the
International Geophysical Year." Also known as
the IGY. It was an 18-month global effort starting
in July of 1957. All of a sudden, these Cold War
rivals are suddenly setting up research stations
all over the place, and they begin to uncover just
how important Antarctica really is. You can see
this if instead of looking at your typical map of
the world, you flip it. Every year, ocean water
freezes and melts around Antarctica. And that
causes these huge changes worldwide because as
water freezes, salt gets pushed out and sinks,
driving all these global currents. The currents in
California and India and Australia are all decided
in Antarctica. That's why scientists call it the
heartbeat of the planet because this is actually
the center of the world. And the size of this
continent is way bigger than you think. It's
bigger than all of Europe, bigger than the United
States, twice the size of Australia. It's huge.
They also learned that the ice covering this huge
continent was way thicker than we imagined. On
average, this ice is over 2 km or 1.3 miles thick.
"Antarctica has a scary amount of water tied up in
its ice." Around 91% of the world's total fresh
water is in the ice that I'm hiking across right
now. That if it melted, it would raise global
sea levels by nearly 60m... ALL of this would be
underwater. Well, there goes my home. During the
hike, there was an expression that the scientists
kept saying, which was 'nothing in Antarctica
stays in Antarctica.' And the more I learned
about this place, the more I understood that.
So, we're now about halfway to our destination,
and the landscape is getting more and more alien.
And this is when we come across a little buddy.
So they were figuring all of this out. And by
1958, the IGY had been so successful that nobody
really wanted to stop and go back to the fighting.
So they didn't. Our grandparents' generation chose
a different future. And in 1959, governments all
around the world signed the Antarctic Treaty,
turning this place into the world's only
science continent. You can see the treaty
happening in real time here. So, we just came
from a UK camp. That's the Indian base right
there called Matri. And then beyond it,
you can see the Russian base called Nova.
Today there are about 70 research stations all
around Antarctica supporting scientists doing
all kinds of groundbreaking research. And during
the IGY this particular base started collecting
constant data on ozone directly above Antarctica.
And by 1985 they had 30 years of data to look back
on and could conclusively say there was a hole and
we really needed to fix it. "Within a few years,
it was clear that ozone depletion was happening
in the northern hemisphere, too. Now, it's getting
closer to home, and it's happening over places
like Washington DC and Boston and Paris. You know,
it's not just an Antarctic problem." Dr. Solomon
and her team ultimately concluded that the problem
was a chemical found in everyday products that
were rising into the atmosphere, breaking apart,
and binding with ozone, and it would get worse
if we didn't stop using them. So, our parents'
generation came together and chose a different
future. Do you remember where you were when the
Montreal Protocol was signed? Do you like what was
it? What was the experience like for you? "Well,
I was actually in Antarctica making measurements,
so I was probably the last one to know. It was
an interesting feeling of being under the ozone
hole, knowing that, you know, half a world away,
an incredible change had just occurred that really
had a lot of potential to change things in the
future. And indeed, it did." By 2009, every single
country in the world signed the Montreal Protocol,
effectively banning those chemicals. But the
victory here wasn't just a ban. It was also
technological innovation to find replacements.
"We found substitutes in every application,
whether it was foam blowing or spray cans or
refrigerators, etc., etc. down the line." And now,
yeah, it's working. "We're actually seeing the
ozone layer recover!" And we know that it's
recovering because of science still happening in
Antarctica. Satellites measure ozone levels from
the sky, and scientists here still monitor
ozone from the ground. The Indian base. I
know that they're doing ozone monitoring. So,
they're watching how the ozone hole is healing
itself from that base right there. We are all
very lucky for the work that you did. "No, no,
it's me that's lucky." But the science here hasn't
stopped. It's always changing. And after 5 hours
of hiking across the ice, we're about to find
something incredible...this is the Blue Rivers.
This is unbelievably beautiful, first of all,
and only exists in the Antarctic summers. So,
liquid water like this does exist
on the surface on Antarctica,
but it's from the melt water from the
glaciers. And it's likely in liquid
form for the first time in hundreds or even
thousands of years. And I'm about to drink it.
Man, that's good. That's really genuinely
delicious. Don't worry, and don't try this
at home. The scientists with us told us that this
water was safe to drink, there aren't any ancient
bacteria in what we were drinking. But while
these seasonal rivers of glacial melt are normal,
something not normal is happening to the ice
around the coasts. Further out around Antarctica,
the ocean water is in the part of its cycle
where it's melting, helping power the oceans.
But during the winters now, less ice is
reliably freezing around Antarctica. In 2023,
it crashed to the lowest level ever recorded,
and it hasn't bounced back, which is starting
to disrupt those global currents that we all
rely on. And this is just one small piece of
how important this continent is. Breakdowns
in Antarctica will disrupt weather patterns,
meaning more intense storms, declines
in global sea life and food supplies,
destruction to ecosystems. This is what we are now
facing. This is our version of that moment right
before the Antarctic Treaty or the Montreal
Protocol. But if you're thinking right now,
the Antarctic Treaty couldn't possibly have
been signed today. You might be right. But
I've been thinking about something that Steven,
the scientist here, has been saying, which is 'the
current future is not the future future.' Meaning
the path that we're on right now doesn't have to
be the path that we're on tomorrow. And we're
really at a tipping point. Our grandparents'
generation came together and instead of turning
Antarctica into a war zone, they signed the
Antarctic Treaty. And our parents' generation came
together and instead of allowing the ozone hole to
get bigger, they signed the Montreal Protocol. Are
we really going to be the generation that doesn't
work together to solve the next problem? Bleep that
like bleep that can't possibly be the generation that
we're going to be. As someone in that generation, not if we have anything to say about it. People
have worked together to solve hard problems
before, and we're going to do it again.
I left Antarctica feeling so inspired by
what people can do when they work together.
If you want to see more optimistic science and
tech stories, subscribe to support our show.